And as usual, the meeting has started.
The recording has started. I am
admitting everybody from the lobby. And
it does take a moment or two for people
to come on in. So, we'll do that. Good
afternoon everyone. Uh my name is
Dominic Zerlo and I am the center
director for the center for medical
cannabis and psilocybin. We apologize
for the bit of delay. We are running
into a few issues technologically and so
uh hopefully other individuals as they
are joining in will be able to uh join
us here shortly but it seems teams
decided to be a little slow today. Um as
usual um just so that everybody uh is
aware we do um we do ask that everybody
keep their language um you know
appropriate. We are recording the
meeting and will be posting it on the
website. And the reason for keeping
language appropriate is because we never
know who's going to be watching it. And
there may be some people who are younger
than the ages of 18 or 21. And
inappropriate language of course would
then you know be uh uh undesirable. In
any case with that I will uh we do have
today Desba who is the chair of the
committee and again this is the
committee equity access and cultural
considerations. Uh we do have a couple
of presentations. Um and so um with
that, Desba, did you want to say
anything before we move into the
presentations?
>> Um I think just maybe like a little bit
of admin housekeeping um stuff. I just
wanted to make sure that everyone knows
that the last meeting I believe all of
the PowerPoints, presentations,
meetings, and recordings are now
available because I know I see
differently on my end than what other
people might see on their end.
And um and then also we are still
continuing to work um to get together
with tribal communities and governance
in that case and anyone's waiting. Um
last meeting we had a presentation from
Denali Wilson and Hanifha Washington. So
that presentation should be up and
available if anyone hasn't yet gone
through there. Um we had a couple of
drafts that I think that the board is
going to be reviewing further. So, make
sure you are on schedule for Friday's
meeting coming up. Um,
yeah, and so we have a couple of
presentations today. So, thank you all
for joining. Um, we can probably do um
introductions later, but I want to make
sure we get the presentations
um in and going so that because we have
a lot of information that we want to get
through. So, I don't know Dominic if you
had any other um updates as well. I do
have one and it is actually a major one
but I wanted to I didn't want to take
away from you uh for any updates you
have. So thank you Despa and the update
that I wanted to provide is that as of
today the record and archive New Mexico
record and archive has promulgated the
production and um laboratory rule. So we
have our first rule. Um now I know some
people because of the questions as far
as some of the the definitions we are
still working through some of those and
so I know that there were some points
about it for example where there was
right after we had presented about it
everybody had been talking about using
guide as the definition and then the
preference to change that to facilitator
so we are doing that in this next set of
rules because that's something that
doesn't really affect uh this current
set and the same with regard to some of
the other things about the facilitator
um practitioner those sort of things. So
we will be having those uh continuing to
have those edit and discussion and
probably not just even in this next set
of rules that we're looking at here over
this next week or two but also in the
third set of rules which as many people
may remember that's going to include
this piece on the equity for example.
Um, and so some of the things we're
doing today are for the next set of
rules or I'm sorry, not this one that
we're that'll be considered by the board
this Friday, but for the set after that.
I know there's so many rules and it can
be so confusing, but just wanted to let
everybody know that is the process uh or
or that's sort of the timeline right now
is we're working on the next set of
rules which is about the education piece
um and the provider piece. Um we also uh
depending on how much we do may include
location with regard to that. So
approved location where that may get
split a little bit with this rule and
the next one and then the next rule will
be the equity piece and then there'll be
some about administration and anything
that we did not finish in this rule as
far as locations or anything else. Um so
some of that just depends how much gets
completed and uh recommendations from
this Friday at the board meeting. So um
but in the meantime um that's that was
the big announcement for today. I will
be repeating that by the way on Friday.
So for if anyone has missed today we'll
repeat that. Um and anyway um so uh
Desba if you're okay I'll turn it over
to Jorge. Oh or did you want to do the
introductions?
>> We can do those as well. We can quickly
do introductions if there's anybody here
that wants to, you know, especially
people who are might be new. I don't
know that there's
>> Okay,
>> there's anybody
>> wants to introduce just go ahead raise
your hand.
>> Looks like we have a reporter in our
midst. Hi, Sky.
>> Sky has been on quite a few of our
meetings. So, welcome Sky
>> and Kate.
>> Yeah. And if people don't want to um uh
raise their hands and introduce
themselves verbally, you can always put
it in the chat. And uh yes, welcome
Craig. [laughter]
Sorry.
And we have Don Moser. Okay. And
Heneife. All right. Great. Chris Pascus.
Hello, Chris.
>> All right, Don. And I've enabled your
mic if you wanted to say hello.
Hello. I know I'm Don Moer. I'm in Las
Vegas, New Mexico. I don't have any
medical background, but uh I really
appreciate the auditing and and
listening to these discussions. Thank
you very much.
>> Glad to have you all.
>> All right. Yeah, we can go ahead and get
started with um the presentation.
Okay. Well, I will turn it over to Jorge
for the introductions. And so, Jorge, if
you do not mind, take it away.
>> All right. Hello everyone. Good
afternoon and thank you for being here.
Hi Gonzalez on the medical psilocybin
program manager. So, thanks for being
here. We do have a couple of speakers uh
and I'll introduce um uh Miguel in just
a second, but we also have uh Leslie
Peterson who works for the uh program as
well who are presenting right after
Miguel. Uh but first uh now we want to
introduce Miguel and please uh he'll go
through his presentation and so if you
would just hold all questions until
after his presentation um that would be
great. Uh and and we're here to answer
questions too. But uh since this is the
equity, access and cultural
considerations committee, we thought uh
it would be great to have uh someone who
um who's [snorts] an expert in the field
but also has a lot of contact uh with
the committee. So um my compadre Miguel
A Costa is is who came to mind right
away. Uh Miguel is the co-director of
Earthare uh has done a lot of work in
community development and community
organizing across the country and is um
now in in Northern New Mexico. And so,
uh, yeah, we go back many years and, uh,
I've seen the great work he he does and
continues to do over the years and and
and, uh, [snorts] uh, just, uh, just
great work. And, uh, I asked him asked
him to do just, uh, a 101, even less
than that, but on on equity and
equality. Uh, and and so this is who I
thought would be appropriate. And so
with that, uh, Miguel A Costa, uh, you,
uh, would you take the show here and I
have a a couple of slides here and you
let me know which one you want and I
will put those on
and you can unmute yourself.
>> Sorry. Um, thank you, Jorge, uh, for
that intro and, uh, and we could just go
through the slides. The last set that
Bianca sent,
>> she saw she sent
>> she sent two of them. Uh there's one
with the tree and then there's one that
that one that are the six slides within
one. Which one would you like to start
off with?
>> Uh well, she she just also sent the
individual slideshow.
>> I don't know if you got that.
>> I have not. Give me a second. And
>> and while you're looking for that, I can
I can just say a couple things. So,
thank you everybody uh for uh for having
me. although you didn't know you were
having me. Thank you Horge for for
thinking of me. Um this is a
conversation equality, equity, the
difference uh therein and um uh and how
it how it relates to sort of community
outcomes that we're that we're trying to
impact. Um it's a very common
conversation. Just by way of uh context
and background, I'm I'll be turning 70
uh in a couple weeks here. And I've been
doing this work uh uh formally, right?
Uh not not as a student, but as an
actual practitioner of community uh
development and social justice,
community health, uh education work, uh
community development work, uh uh uh
sobriety work, uh etc. for 50 years,
more or less. Uh so I've I've seen all
the different var
uh iterations and variations in
conversation and different priorities
from the federal government and state
governments. I worked for DOH for a few
years in health promotion um working
with with community health councils. Uh
I've worked in education and higher ed
and community based organizations for a
number of years. So I've number of
years. So this is a a a moving target
and a conversation that that has been
ongoing. Uh, and here in New Mexico, the
thing that makes it different is the
history and the context and current
conditions of of uh of the populations
that we seek to impact. Um, so uh and
also in terms of appropriate language, I
may use things like social justice. I
may, you know, use terms like democracy,
participation, etc. And I don't know if
those are I know at some levels of
government that's considered
inappropriate language, but I'm hoping
that it works okay here with us. Uh so
uh just just just go to that first
slide. Uh Jorge,
>> so Miguel, I I just want to inform you
that Bianca sent that to me as a goo, uh
within a Google Drive and and as part of
the as part of the state, we're not able
to um as policy to access those just
because of the
>> the the possib other possibility. So I
can share the other one though.
>> Yeah, let's just go with the other one.
The one that has the three the equality,
equity, and justice, right?
>> Okay. Okay.
>> Uh we can start there.
>> That should be on your screen right now.
>> There you go. So in in uh this is
basically a snapshot of the conversation
that we're having and and more so than
conversation the practice uh that we try
to to to work on right uh I'm I remember
back when equality was the word uh was
the the was the buzzword uh you know
civil rights movement uh I was in
Chicago at that time um and um and that
and that was the you know equality for
all um you know, all men are created
equal. You know, all the things that
that we that we try to pull uh from both
from history and and current context,
equality was really the word uh the term
uh the framing that people were were
pushing. Uh with time, um even with
terms like, you know, all men are
created equal. Um it became apparent
that that wasn't really uh good enough,
right? that we needed to go beyond uh
concepts of equality because conditions
weren't the same for everybody. Just
making something available uh didn't
mean that it was equally accessible to
everybody. We moved towards uh concepts
of equity, right? Where where people's
uh life experiences, life conditions,
uh uh living uh spaces, etc. were taken
into consideration so that people could
get what they needed based on their abil
uh ability to access, ability to thrive,
uh ability to take advantage of those
resources. There's an organization here
in town in Santa Fe uh that that uh
defines equity as equal uh access to
resources and equal exposure to risk,
right? Uh which is another way of
thinking about it that that uh that's
very useful. uh beyond equity uh we've
talked about systems change right um and
and this is something that's very very
familiar I'm sure to folks in in health
and and health promotion and and uh and
health justice uh so the idea that if if
if we can change systems so that the
barriers don't uh develop in the first
place uh then we're creating a system
that's more just for everybody right uh
if we can just go to the next slide
please or the the the one with the six
uh or the nine slides.
>> I will
>> and this will be a little difficult. Uh
the the the technological issues that
people were having were basically that
we don't that I'm the the low tech
Mexican in the group here. So we
couldn't get things going in in the way
that we needed to. Uh and we're still
operating on that level. So I you know I
come from uh the pencil and paper and
papel as we used to call flip charts.
right now everything's like whiteboards
and and and and what have you. Um so
everything is has progressed except uh
uh some of us right that are sort of
stuck. Um but this gives you an
overview. I'm not going to go read
through this uh everything word by word
but it gives you an overview really of
of the framing the concept and the and
the conversation that can be had uh
around uh equality, equity and justice.
um you know we we we talk for example
about uh you know giving everybody equal
resources in this case we're talking
about health interventions or or u
health promotion or health resources uh
I I was in a conversation earlier today
about economic uh resources
uh and if anybody's familiar for example
here in Santa Fe the economic
development department at the city over
the last few years has done an amazing
job of making resources available to
entrepreneurs right uh The the problem
is the most of the folks that are most
ready to utilize and capitalize on those
resources are either people that already
have privilege that already have
backgrounds in business. Uh many uh if
not most are recent arrivals to New
Mexico. Many are coming here because of
these uh opportunities. So it's not an
equitable uh investment in our
community. Right. there's there's
specific po pockets of the population
that are uh thriving more from these
resources using you know gaining greater
access to them than than others in terms
of health and health promotion uh you
know when we talk about equality uh I'll
give you another example from Santa Fed
during the pandemic uh we had a real
challenge trying to get resources to the
airport road corridor uh and we had a
really difficult time you know uh trying
to explain to the city the county and
the state that placing uh a clinic uh or
a testing site uh say at the
intersection of of um of est of St.
Francis and uh or or let's just say Rios
and and Rodeo did not grant equal access
to those resources for people. Um
there's lots of details, lots of
examples that we can go through on that,
but but I'll just leave it at that,
right? that that creating something
doesn't mean that uh and offering it to
the community doesn't mean that it's
equally accessible to everybody out
there. Equity takes in into
consideration people's in uh you know
specific uh life life circumstances
uh accessibility issues, transportation
issues, child care, etc. So that the
resources could be made more equitably
available to all to all populations.
Right. Uh the justice frame here uh you
know talks about the kinds of
anticipating possibly the kinds of
barriers that that that uh structurally
uh are are present for people that we
might be able to impact so that uh they
don't become issues in the first place,
right?
uh you know sort of how universal
uh design uh has has has created spaces
so that like say curriculum instruction
and other kinds of things are
universally accessible uh for folks that
that may have physical or or other kinds
of um challenges. Same kind of concept
here, right? um or similar not same a
similar kind of concept uh in terms of
of uh removing barriers that might exist
so that we have a more socially just
system. Ultimately uh it'd be nice for
systems to be created in partnership
with the communities that are most
impacted by the issues in in the first
place. Right? Uh so the idea of of in
this case it's called belonging but the
idea that that uh that the the impacted
communities uh the the communities that
are that are experiencing the the
challenge in the first place are the
ones that are in the best position to
design the responses. They're the ones
that uh live uh the with the challenges,
experience the challenges, have found
ways to respond to the challenges, and
they're in the best situation to
actually be able to design uh the
responses. There's an example here of
Maria uh and three different approaches
to supporting uh her uh which you can
might by now uh kind of guess, right?
The equality approach, equity approach,
and a justice approach. And why this
matters? Um the our our goal is to have
a healthier community for everyone,
right? Uh and everybody's health affects
everybody else. Population health,
community health uh is behind our
opportunities or or or challenges in
terms of our ability to to create a
sustainable world to to have uh a higher
quality of life uh for everybody. So
taking you know so making sure that
we're that we're providing the resources
necessary for those that are facing the
most challenges and and redesigning
systems so that those challenges don't
exist in the first place we all benefit
from that. uh when and and and again
during a pandemic it was very evident,
right? That when when things go wrong,
uh they're going to impact everybody,
right? Uh so it's not just uh the the
comm the lower income or communities of
color or whatever that get impacted by
by uh inequity in the system. Everybody
eventually is impacted by by this. Um, I
don't know that there's more that I want
to uh necessarily share at this point.
Uh, because I'd really be interested to
see if there's any questions or comments
uh about this. Uh, this this framing
here uh we use with all the neighbor all
the neighborhoods that we work with, the
communities that we work with is part of
our work for climate justice and
environmental justice as well as
education and economic justice. Uh, of
course, uh, the health work that we do.
uh this is part of how we build
capacity, understanding and awareness uh
among the populations that we work with.
So Jorge, that's good enough. I'd love
to be able to respond to or have a
conversation uh around any of these
issues if there's any questions.
>> Great. Thank you, Miguel. Yeah. And so
with that, uh, Miguel has opened it up
if you'd like to raise your hand and ask
for clarification or questions and how
that's how this, uh, relates to all the
conversations we've had here and some of
the, uh, around us, especially around
the, um, uh, treatment equity fund. So,
[laughter]
>> Desba,
>> thank you so much for Yeah. Um, thank
you so much for the this presentation
and um, you know, part of the thing that
I think of immediately like especially
the the comment that you made from the
very beginning is, you know, that's part
of like the accessibility.
Um, and I'm just kind of throwing this
out there. You know, we're in such this
age that everything is always digital.
We put a lot of emphasis on like our
social media. We're looking for social
media managers. We're looking at a way
to like get to the new to the younger
crowd and the emphasis is always on like
technology and and how can we like move
forward and ahead um when it comes to
like kids and Tik Tok and chat and all
kinds of other now it's like it's now
it's the group chat now it's kind of
going back and it's interesting for me
to see the dissemination of information
amongst peers and different in different
groups groups of people. And when I'm
thinking of accessibility,
I'm thinking not only of like my
13-year-old in the group chat, and
that's where they're kind of like, you
know, sharing memes and sharing their
information, but I'm thinking back to,
you know, my my father, you know, my
mom, you know, they're they're getting
to their 80s at this point. And my dad
is still, you know, we're still on I'm
still on the paper. you can't see it
because it's the thing. But
>> um you know and so it's like when we're
trying to think about accessibility,
it's still to me you how do we get the
the message out and when we have and are
we thinking about the future with system
collapse?
>> Yeah.
>> You know, carrier pigeons, owls, right?
That's going to be like a little
hilarious. But I'm thinking radio ads.
I'm thinking there's still a need for
newspapers. I'm thinking there's still a
need for all of these old systems that a
lot of our elders still rely on. my
ex-husband is trying to find an
apartment here in Santa Fe and I'm like,
I was told there's a specific way to go
and it's basically just drive around the
neighborhood because a lot of times you
might see the signs that are actually
literally in in the yards because you
know who has time to try to figure out I
can't even figure out how to do
Craigslist anymore. I mean that to me is
just it's posting here, put this here.
Even the teams meeting is just so
complicated for me,
>> right?
>> Um so when I'm thinking accessibility,
I'm just thinking like how we look at
>> um these small social structures that
are starting to come back in Vogue again
now, but like in a different context
with our younger people. And then I'm
also thinking about our older generation
who still gets their information from,
you know, the the younger people, from
their from their grandkids, from their
from their own children, and then also
from radio ads and so forth. And, you
know, as much as it's great to push
forward ahead in technology, we need to
make sure that we're still looking at
how the these uh all these
multigeneration systems are are
operating and functioning.
>> Yeah. No, and and thank you for all
that. I would actually even suggest that
we take it a bit further. Uh like my
generation and and and older folks uh
it's not just that uh that we don't have
the same technological access and all
that, but there was a time when we were
the source of this information, right?
Uh there wasn't a department of health.
It was our elders, our healers, uh, and
and other folks in the neighborhoods in
the community that actually
disseminated, not just disseminated
information around community health.
They were the ones that were that had
their fingers on the pulse of the
community's health and could, you know,
would know when something was was
breaking down within that community
system. We took all that away from
people, right? We we we that's part of
the extractive uh history and economy
here in New Mexico, right? So we took
all that information away from it from
people and put it in the hands of
experts. Then the question be the
challenge becomes okay, how do we get
the information out of the experts and
back out to the community. Uh I I would
say that that you know that when we're
talking about systems change is not just
how do we make sure that people are
getting the right information, but how
do we make sure that the right people
are the ones that are that are creating
the information in the first place? you
know, when we're talking about uh like
some of the interventions that you all
are are are considering here or talking
about. I was just in Ecuador and I've
done work in Mexico uh for example uh
and a lot of the the challenges that I
pose to systems here in the United
States uh is that there's there's a
different cultural framing. It's not
just language. It's not just taking
information and translating it. There's
a different cultural framing. Uh
sometimes, you know, the the the the
issues don't even exist in in a
particular group's culture.
uh but that's where we need to start
right so things need to be framed if
we're talking about uh u mushroom
psychedelics or whatever in terms of
treatment uh how that's perceived in the
communities is different in each one
right the history and the cultural
approaches to these things are different
in parts of of Mexican culture for
example these are uh traditions these
are these are uh ceremonial traditions
that that are still carried today in
other parts that been more westernized
uh you know people won't even you know
look for any kind of behavioral health
support let alone uh you know be treated
by what they're considering now illicit
drugs or what have you that's the level
of the work of the systems work I think
that we need to be considering uh it
goes beyond sort of equity and and
beyond sort of the the maybe the general
conversations around justice and it's
how do we reclaim how do we reclaim
knowledge uh
our version of AI, ancestral
intelligence, right? How do we make this
uh take this uh and and and make it a
part of our traditions again so that
your father uh the grandfathers, the
grandmothers, you know, become the
sources and the holders of of the
knowledge that keeps us healthy rather
than relying, you know, and then the
kids have easier access, right? because
they can go to grandpa, they can go to
grandma, they can go to circle, they can
go ceremony uh and and uh and know how
to uh you know know amongst ourselves
how to heal and stay healthy rather than
waiting for a brochure or waiting for
the workshop or waiting for waiting for
the zoom waiting for the team's link. Um
so you know so there's a deeper level of
work I think uh that has to happen not
only because it's the right thing to do
but it's it could be the right way to
survive like you're saying when systems
collapse if we don't have that level of
of uh of connection uh and and knowledge
and meaning at the at the at the local
neighborhood clan uh you know what
whatever you want to call it level. Uh
it's not just the systems that'll
collapse. all of us are going to be
struggling to survive.
>> Thank you. Um, hold on. I'll get to you,
Greg, for one second. I just wanted to
um go back to what you were saying also
too about and I'm glad you said this um
and it's a reframing something that I
had also said previous in previous um uh
conversations and meetings was exactly
what you said. you know, we have this
colonialized western way of thinking
that kind of came in and said, you know,
everything that you thought ancestrally
is bad. It's it's it's it's sinful.
It's, you know, you're savages. You're
you know, all of this way of thinking,
this indoctrination of of western
western thought. and and then now in
some ways we're being asked to pay
attention to our indigenous cultures and
ways of being. But that's kind of lost
on some of us. You know, I made an
example myself. You know, I'm an urban
I'm an urban native. I didn't grow on my
reservation and you know, that part was
was kind of lost. So, we're doing a lot
of reconnecting to our ancestralism. And
so in essence, you know, this is also a
parallel of, you know, in digital format
in in terms of the information of making
those reconnections not only with like
the 13-year-old to the 80-year-old and
me somewhere in between, but it's also
making sure that we we reconnect with
the new information, the new
technologies, how that works like you
were saying with the elders so that they
are not also at the same time left
behind. because some of us, you know,
we're we're we're savvy. We're able to
figure out how to use the WhatsApp
messenger and some of us aren't. Um, and
sometimes it doesn't have to do with
age. Sometimes we're just, you know,
we're lucky to know how those systems
work. But making sure that those
connections, like you were saying, are
are reconnected. And that to me, like
you were saying, is the true ancestral
knowledge of of remembering who we are.
And that's part of the whole process to
me of like honoring the mushroom,
honoring the psychedelics and and
psychedelics in general is a
reconnecting to self. And then from
there, you know, you go into integration
and and how that works because now, you
know, we're we're in this new place.
>> Um, so I just kind of wanted to to say
thank you for saying that. Um, that it's
not always just, you know, sometimes we
end up romanticizing without realizing
it indigenous wisdom. And we have to
recognize and realize people are always
at a different place in their in their
reconnecting if they choose to and also
just in a different place where we land.
And then we there we have an opportunity
to move in those different places as
best as possible. Um but to strengthen
those connections with our elders and
then especially establishing and making
sure that our newer generation for sure
too [snorts] um you know that they also
remember where they came from that they
also remember who they are and that is
strengthening the community and that is
um making sure that we all have the you
know the right like you said the right
information. Um Greg did you want to go
ahead and chime in?
Sure.
Hi. Thank you for that.
Um, yeah. [clears throat] Thank you so
much. That was beautiful. It's good to
have this voice in the room. Um,
and I have a couple kind of points I
want to get on. Um,
essentially
bringing this back to the program at the
end of my question. It's kind of
twofold,
but I wanted to get your response on
things that you've seen in processes
changing over time in the activism
communities and what what type of
methodologies, not like exact things,
not like using a printer, using a phone,
but like the kind of like core ethos of
the methodology
where people are adapting to new forms
of communication
inside a community who's actively
responding to rapid change. things that
come to mind are um incidents like Black
Rockck where traditional and modern
technologies were just rapidly folded
together to communicate in ways that
were changing and and creating safety
and in response to active um you know
assault. um or more recently in
Minnesota, one of the most beautiful
forms of like communication
adaptation that I've seen in recent
history was that like
there were massive text threads, right?
And just like we were talking about like
Desb was talking about now it's the text
thread. This is where it is. But what
was what didn't happen is the most
vulnerable populations were not left
behind. There were there were networks
of communities in those, you know,
modern rapid communication networks that
were still organizing to make sure that
had food because we knew that this
family in this house on our street that
we've like since George Floyd, we've set
up like communication networks and we
kept those alive so that when something
like this happened,
rapid change and adaptation and
inclusion could occur. her
moving into like how we can bring this
into the the specific program that we're
talking about in medical psilocybin. I
do feel like there may be a massive gap
between those who actually need the
services most and are the most
vulnerable populations may not know that
they need these service or that they're
available or that they're nonstick they
can unstigmatize they can unlearn lang
colonial language that's been that's
been pushed on them for centuries that
like even though this might not be like
their history and their tradition that
there is something of value that we need
to approach through the process of
community education and not just from
the department but like just spreading
education through community knowledge
and this idea that we get from things
like so mushroom cultivation has this
concept of traditional ecological
knowledge. We have this subversive
underground community that has been
studying these se things that are
growing that are a part of our ecosystem
for decades and decades and decades. But
we haven't been able to like put that
information in a published material, but
there's still been ways that we've been
able to like keep that ecological
knowledge alive and thriving. And it
shifts. You know, it used to be letters
in a book. You used to order a book from
the Homestead Book Company and you get a
sport print and you get information came
directly from Terrence McKenna and now
you have like message boards and things
like that and people calling each other,
people who are afraid to be on the
message boards but still communicate
with each other. So, how can we get that
type of system in place to spread
information? That was very
[clears throat] long-winded. I apologize
and thank you.
>> Yeah. I know that the that's a lot of um
a lot of good examples. Uh there there
was also, you know, interesting um uh in
response to to ICE in Chicago, for
example,
um you know, in some of the earliest uh
accounts from the the the
what do you call the colonizers from
Europe, the Spanish in particular,
right? They they talked about how uh
communities uh uh communicated or tribes
or what have you communicated uh through
drums, whistles, and other kinds of
things that they couldn't figure out,
right? Uh and one of the ways one of the
most successful ways of communicating uh
during the ICE raids in Chicago uh was
whistles and not only whistles to alert
that there was something happening but
but uh but they actually started
developing sort of you know um uh
different kinds of whistles and and and
different patterns and what have you to
to get different you know so there was a
language that was starting to develop
again a communications language uh using
whistles gangs in Chicago started
changing their their uh I mean they tag,
right? They they claim territory and and
pose messages and all that. They started
using some of their uh skills to be able
to communicate information about ICE,
about safety and and and and things like
that. It was amazing, right, People were
reclaiming uh traditional ways of of
communicating like you're saying. Uh key
to all that though is uh and I worked a
different project with department of
health um uh a couple years ago for it
was a three-year project uh around
vaccines and one of the things that we
were really focused on was the idea of
trusted messengers right and and who it
is that's delivering that's sharing the
information that's helping to develop
etc. uh and and our focus on on that uh
and we got a little bit of recognition
right before things went wacky in DC
around um the the idea of building
capacity among the again you know
focusing on on folks living in the uh
communities that we're trying to have an
impact on building capacity skills etc
and then trusting our ourselves trusting
those those folks to be able to do uh
the work uh and and and the power of
them being trusted by that community in
the first place. Right. So that the
systems that we develop, you know, and
and as you were talking, I was thinking,
you know, if we're thinking about uh
about we always talk about food as
medicine in in traditional communities,
right? We talk about food as medicine.
Uh there's yertoos and and and uh and
and everything in our in our
neighborhoods, in our communities that
know about uh you know different herbs
and different foods and different um uh
variations and the the order you know of
things that need to be ingested etc for
for there to be health the the intended
health uh impacts. Uh and and one of the
things that we need to do is talk about
this as as food, right? mushrooms as
food, not as a drug, not as as a
something coming from from the vaccine
side of the world, right? From the chem
chemical and and scientist and and
doctor side of the world, but coming
from traditional knowledge and coming
from from ancestral practices uh and
being part of the conversation around
food and food as medicine, right? how
you know those two those two approaches
would have I think greatly different uh
responses from from the comm at least
from the communities that I work with
right from the immigrant communities and
and other people of color uh it would
have a a much different uh response um
and that really has to be you know like
you're saying the technologies that we
may use to create uh communication
systems if they're not based in models
that are uh that are intuitive to people
because they're the way that they've
always done it, they're not going to
work or they're they're going to be
limited in their impact, right? Um uh
like Desba said, you know, there's a lot
of folks that are really skilled in in
in uh tech technological and digital
communications and all that. Um
and and that serves uh that does have a
specific you can get a message to
someone that way, right? But without the
relationship being there, that message
doesn't have a whole lot of uh land to
pl, you know, space to land in. Uh and
it won't flourish. It won't spread. It
won't be understood. You know, the
meaning won't be there. Uh they'll have
uh you know, sort of the way that people
are trying to teach in the schools now.
you know, you you've got the AI teacher
that gives you the data to memorize uh
but without knowing how to how to apply
that data and or that information and
without having you know sort of the the
the relational aspects of that learning
uh it's not going to have the intended
impact it'll be less or it'll be in some
cases none.
>> [snorts]
>> So I guess one minor response to that is
like what is the risk that we run as
if we're disseminating information
through the United States government or
representation of that body to people
who innately don't trust that body for
information
>> right
>> how do we handle that
conundrum
>> well I mean I think that that uh
communities are already ahead of us and
and they've already stopped
uh trusting a lot of that information
and they're seeking other places for the
uh for that information. um we need to
be tapping you we need to be making sure
that the the correct and the and the the
the supportive information is available
in other spaces and that's why I'm
saying you know having like local
sources of of knowledge u uh which goes
is you know and when we're talking about
systems change is not just uh the kinds
of things that we've been talking about
but it's also the the you know we've
been you know since World War II we've
been moving toward towards the the big
box uh style of everything, right? Uh
you know, it's better to have a a huge
school with 5,000 students rather than
having, you know, 500 schools with 20
students each, right? Uh and and that's
been part of the problem, right? That
that we've accumulated not just capital,
we've accumulated information, data,
systems, etc. in these big box type
spaces and that's working against us. uh
that's really working against us. We
need to have in every neighbor every
neighborhood. Part of why Minnesota was
so successful and Chicago was so
successful and other places as well is
because of the the communication system
structures that were in place to support
those systems. uh in those places it was
parishes right you know people grow up
uh in those places whether they were
Catholic or not they grew up in those
space in in those places having a sense
of the parish and the parish was the the
the the kind of the extended family the
clan the what have you right uh the
source of of things and and the and the
destination of things and the place that
I'll always be etc uh if it wasn't for
those uh for that level of or social
organization
uh there were other things would have
had to have been in place for it to be
successful. Um so, you know, so we're
always arguing here in Santa Fe that we
need to have every neighborhood has to
have uh and this has been the Cuban
model, right? Every neighborhood has to
have the things that it needs to be
sustainable, safe, uh thrive, etc. Um
so, every neighborhood has to have a
clinic, a school, a library, a park,
right? um place for toddlers to play, uh
a place for children to be safe, uh a
place for for uh job job training and
and uh education, entertainment, uh you
know, every every neighborhood needs
that uh in in order to to thrive. Uh so
so that's one way of responding to to
the reliance on on the federal
government's data or information or what
have you and the lack of trust is to
make neighborhood-based relationships
viable again. [snorts]
>> Yeah. Um I kind of wanted to go ahead
and jump off that as well. Um
to to talk about that just a little and
then go into something maybe a little
different. Um
because
when you say like the trusted I mean
there's just so many things to kind of
there's so many like different tangents
but the last thing you're talking about
with like the parishes and the trusted
sources and the trusted communities and
I'm I'm I'm trying to think of that
sort of versus like this idea of
marketing and educational materials and
you know where and this isn't to say
anything
this is to kind of not I guess critique
I guess the government it's more like to
critique the government sometimes I feel
like you know it's like we've done you
know the metrics x y and z and then it's
done right I mean I've also worked in
government so I guess I can feel safe to
say that you know it's like we've hit
these metrics and we've done x amount of
things we've done this educational thing
we've met with these people we've done
our job but I feel like it's also So,
and then there's also this idea of
overreach, right? And then there's the
idea of lack and trust in the government
and the discernment that is needed,
which is still kind of like this
education,
um, which is still like this form of
listening and acknowledging and being
able to dis differentiate
what's being thrown at us. Um, and and
this also can go into, you know, the use
of psychedelics as you're in in the
moment, as you're in in the in the
treatment. Um, being able to discern
what of the information is valuable and
what is it that is, you know, that you
can use and which can kind of like I
don't want to say throw away, but, you
know, maybe that's just not what we are
looking at at the moment.
But when you're saying trusted sources
and and I feel like a lot of people are
it still takes that one- on-one
interaction is I guess was where I was
trying to go at the one-on-one
interaction with people focused effort
in the communities
versus this idea that we're getting from
technology that we've gone from
people on bullhorns out in this in the
corner or out in the plaza shouting
information. We've gone from from that
to like newspapers and then from
newspapers we've gone to radio and these
are all still very like massive reaches
of information to people but now we're
kind of getting into this false sense of
individualism.
I'm probably using all these terms
wrong, but you know, of of moving it
into, you know, a person's phone,
tailored algorithms to an individual
person to then coers them to think a
certain way and these marketing tools.
But this connection that I have with my
phone is not the same as the trusted
sources information that I have with an
individual person and the amount of of
effort and the amount of of education
that it goes in in making those
connections. You know you have people
who are in charge of AI now saying that
like human beings are cost too much to
take care of and that's why we have to
go into technology and that's not the
whole point of like you know when it
comes to psychedelics the point of
psychedelics is whole person
is whole being is returning to the
community and if the only way that we
can return to the community is
one-on-one kind of efforts in those
trusted sources it's like to me it's
like pitching
you know, humanity versus like the
technology. And it's not really it's how
do we use the technology to to ma still
maintain those connections, but also at
the same time like marry and meld it so
that we have the education so that we're
still moving in this way. So the
individual person is still, you know,
working towards wholeness and being able
to really listen to have the discernment
to be able to have the effort and the
energy to have those one-on-one
conversations.
And yeah, that takes a lot of effort and
it takes a lot of time. It's not
instantaneous. I mean, it can be if we
have telepathy. I can I can say that
much but you know it's um and that's
what I'm kind of hearing what I'm from
from what you're saying in these
conversations that we still cannot
forget the one-on-one human interactions
that we have which is the whole point
and basis of why we're doing this and
why we're facilitating even these
conversations.
>> Yeah. Well, and and the one-on-one
connection is half the cure,
you know, just just being able to in in
in uh in Mashika
uh language and traditions, they had a a
term apapacho, right? Uh and apapacho
basically uh meant
uh my spirit embracing your spirit, my
soul embracing your soul, right? At that
level of connection, not just, you know,
sort of, hey, I know you, you lived on
the street, right? you know, but working
to connect um
at that level, you know, the same
symbolic way that that uh that you know,
folks come together forehead to
forehead, right? Um
you know, that's that's the intent,
right?
>> And and then I I'm sorry, the whole
point I was kind of moving on to is this
idea of belonging, right?
>> Yeah. That's because I saw that in your
in your in your um presentation
was, you know, how do we maintain that
sense of like if there's just one person
in the community who's has that change,
it might be difficult for them to to
hold on to that joy or that hope that
they may have. So, how do we then
continue to enforce not enforce but
facilitate their growth, right? If that
person is is the only one to start
affecting the change for themselves and
that sense of belonging, we need to
still move in those places to provide um
provide that for them somehow.
>> Yeah. No. And and and then then there's
also the the which is always on my mind
and I'm always reminding people, right?
There's also the ethical dilemma of what
we're doing is you know we keep trying
to find better ways of people to survive
an unfair and unjust system right
uh so you know that in itself is is an
uh a lingering question right that we
always have to be talking about changing
the big system as well right um not just
finding ways for people to cope with
Thank you.
Uh so with that, thank you for taking
your time and being here with us and and
u yeah and sharing your wisdom and
bringing this to us. So thank you so
much.
>> I hope it was helpful.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> And I'll be in touch.
>> Okay. All right. Be well.
>> Thank you. Bye. Bye. Thank you all.
Thank you for allowing that space for
him, Desba. Um with that, we do have uh
Leslie Peterson who is our senior
compliance officer. Uh so um she's going
to do a presentation and it's really the
information uh that we have gathered
again from from the previous uh
committee meetings that you've had. And
so she has brought that together and she
will now be presenting.
Take it away Leslie.
I'm on mute. Okay, got to start off with
a muted mic. Um, thank you so much
everybody. Um, good afternoon. Thank you
Miguel for that wonderful presentation
on um, equality and justice. I feel like
now is a little weird because the senior
compliance officer, government
compliance officer is now going to talk
about the money. So, um, hopefully we
can transition well and um, just go with
that. So, thank you again uh everyone. I
invite you to do some immersion reading
with me because I will be reading these
slides. Um [snorts]
I believe that um immersion reading is
good for a
better focus
as I look away. better focus and uh
reduce distraction
and uh better concentration and stronger
comprehension. So let's let's do this. I
am going to be presenting the um medical
psilocybin treatment equity fund
presentation.
Okay. So that's pretty exciting and for
I will be um these are the objectives of
the presentation.
Uh we want to have a foundational
definition of the medical psilocybin
treatment equity fund per the Senate
bill 219. I think it's very important
for us to have to to have that
foundation again and refresh our minds
about what it's all about per the Senate
Bill 219. Also, let's recap a few facts
about the equity fund.
Um, we're going to talk about a few
equity and access reminders. And
finally, the most exciting part is the
recommendations for the equity, access,
and cultural committees considerations
committee. Um, this presentation will
only address recommendations regarding
the income eligibility criteria for the
medical psilocybin treatment equity
fund. Again, we're just going to talk
about income eligibility criteria. So,
please hold all questions and comments
until the end of the presentation.
All right, here we go.
Um,
the medical psilocybin treatment equity
fund is created as a non-reverting fund
in the state treasury. The fund consists
of appropriations, gifts, grants, and
donations. The fund shall be used to
fund treatments of qualified patients
who meet income requirements determined
by rule of the department. The
department shall administer the fund and
money in the fund is subject to
appropriation by the legislature.
Expenditures from the fund shall be by
warrants signed by the secretary of
finance and administration on vouchers
signed by the secretary of health or the
secretary's authorized representative.
This is all pretty standard um finance
procedures.
Next, let's recap the facts. Um so,
right now, the New Mexico Medicals
psilocybin treatment equity fund has a
one-time allocation at $630,000.
The original bill had requested 1
million per year in non-reverting funds.
The department timeline to utilize the
equity fund is by the end of fiscal year
28 for the current allocation.
Additional funding allocated and
approved to the legislative budget cycle
should be non-reverting.
Most funding reverts to the general fund
if it is unspent at the end of the
fiscal year. Non-reverting means any
unspent money at the end of the fiscal
year does not return to the state
general fund and instead stays with the
program. Okay.
Equity and access. Our goal is to ensure
the medical psilocybin treatment fund is
allocated
clearly and responsibly prior
prioritizing individuals and communities
with the greatest need. Together, these
efforts help ensure the limited money
creates measurable and equitable impact
where they are needed most. Equity and
access in public health funding require
applying transparent need-based criteria
to allocate resources consistently and
in line with regulatory standards.
All right. So for income eligibility
criteria the recommendations for the
equity access and cultural committee
considerations committee. These are our
recommendations.
Please remember as applications are
received for the medical psilocybin
treatment equity fund all considerations
for utilization will be dependent on the
money available.
If an applicant for the equity fund
receives benefits such as Medicaid,
Supplemental Nutrition Assistance
Program, SNAP, or Temporary Assistance
for Needy Family, TANF, and/or
supplement security income, SSI,
then with proper verification
documentation, up to 100% of their
medical psilocybin treatment may be
paid. Okay,
here is a list of possible verification
documents.
We have the Medicaid eligibility letter,
SNAP verification letter, TANF approval
letter, SSI award letter, andor the
previous year tax return.
Other agencies income eligibility
criteria um will be honored by the
Department of Health um such as the
income eligibility criteria for the New
Mexico Healthcare Authority Income
Support Division. We will also honor the
EL income eligibility criteria of the
United States Federal Security
Administration.
To continue on with the recommendations,
up to 100% of the medical psilocybin
treatment may be paid for applicants who
are less than or equal to 200% of the
federal poverty level. This is after
other sources of payments have been
explored or utilized such as Medicaid or
insurance.
And I've inserted here a link to um the
guidelines we used for the federal
poverty levels.
also to be determined um are
considerations and criteria for unserved
groups and communities such as veterans,
Native Americans, residents of rural
frontier areas, and other groups as
identified. Here
is our tiered eligibility chart. Um,
less than or equal to 200% of the
federal poverty level. Um, up to 100% of
treatment will be paid. And then further
on down, up to 250%
of the federal
>> Yep.
>> The slides haven't changed yet.
>> Oh, they haven't changed. I'm sorry.
>> Thank you.
>> Has [clears throat] this changed?
No,
>> not yet. Okay.
>> And how about that?
>> Yes.
>> There we go.
>> Okay. Perfect. Thank you.
>> Did we see this one?
>> No.
>> No, we did not.
>> Okay.
>> All right.
>> All right. So, but as I was saying to be
determined the considerations criteria
for underserved groups um and
communities such as veterans, Native
Americans, residents of rural frontier
areas and other groups as identified is
to yet to be determined.
And here is our tiered eligibility
chart. Um less than or equal to 200% of
the federal poverty level up to 100% of
the treatment will be paid. And then
we've broken it down to 2011 to 250% of
the federal poverty level. 80% of the
treat up to 80% of the treatment will be
paid and then so forth and so on. Um
down to if you do go greater than or
equal to 401% of the federal poverty
level that is where we suggest um that
uh the participant is not eligible for
the equity fund. So that is our tiered
eligibility chart. Okay. Um, I did have
some household income examples here uh
to support the tiered eligibility chart.
So, if we have a single person at the
federal poverty level making 15,960,
if that person is up to 200% um of the
federal poverty level, then up to 100%
of the treatment may be paid. And so,
these are the income levels accordingly
to the chart.
So even up to 400% of the federal
poverty level uh for a single person
would be $63,840
per year, then we could still pay up to
20% of the treatment plan.
And then here are some other examples.
For a twoerson household
um at the federal poverty level at 200%
etc.
Okay. So,
are there any questions?
>> Let's see.
>> Thank you for the um presentation. I'll
go ahead and um let Jen uh Senator
Seinborn uh take a first stab at it. I
saw you had a comment there, so
hopefully you'll address that.
>> Okay. Well, yes.
Senator Steinborn,
>> please go ahead.
>> Thanks everybody.
>> Yeah, multi asking again on multiple
computers. Can you all hear me? Okay. Or
is there a lot of background noise?
Okay, I'll just be real brief and then
I'll then I'll turn off my mic. Um,
yeah. Well, there was a slide in your
presentation that said that the
department's goal was to spend the money
by 2028, which is really in conflict
with the law. The law says it's
non-reverting period. So, I I think I
would probably I get a little concerned
with that 2028. I don't know that it's
even appropriate. Um I I I do think we
should just be concerned though with
burn rate and how much how much demand
there is. I do worry about the chart
that was just presented about
eligibility because I think taking it up
to 400%.
Um is a little rich maybe quite frankly
um and I worry that we're going to go
through it very very fast and uh
>> but the intent of the equity fund is to
really help people who otherwise
couldn't afford it at all. So I just I'm
worried about that. I'd almost rather
start I mean I don't know. I'll just
throw this out there. I not hard and
fast, but this is my kind of instinct
just looking at is I'd almost rather
start
with low income up to like even 200% of
the poverty level or 250 maybe. But and
then and then kind of cap it at that
maybe. Um
>> yeah,
>> but any I'll just throw that out there.
I'm a little concerned with how rich it
is going up there to 20% for people
making that much income. So
>> Sure. No, I hear you. Um
>> Senator um Steinborn, these are
suggestions, only suggestions.
>> And so, um and I'm sure Dominic also has
something to say.
>> Thank you.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. And thank you, Senator Steinborn.
And I had put in the chat that um the
the funds are not they are
non-reverting. It's just that we have a
goal to have enough patients through uh
the program by the end of FY28. But if
we do not then uh the funds will
continue to be utilized through the next
year or until they are depleted. Um so
that's that's what it is that's what the
department is looking at not necessarily
as far as what the statute is as far as
it if it would revert by the end of that
time period. And then the other part is
uh this committee originally had
actually been looking at up to 600%. And
part of the reason we put it at the 400
is we wanted to show exactly what you're
pointing out, Senator Steinborn is that
are these actually appropriate amounts
by putting them actually into numbers
that everyone can see rather than just
discussing and is that something you
know is the 400% and actually Leslie can
you go to the slide uh that shows that
for the single individual? Um I think
it's there we go. um you know so when we
look at that at 400% for a single
individual that is at essentially
$64,000 a year. So is that appropriate
or do we need to look at some other um
scaling for this? And that's a part of
why we wanted to have the discussion
because these are items that came in and
and by the way some of the other uh um
comments that had come in in the other
some of the other meetings was actually
doing it only capping it at 200%. And so
we had wide variability in this and
that's part of why we want to do this as
far as a uh the conversation.
>> Thank you, Dominic. Maybe I'll just
throw out this one little suggestion and
then and then mute myself, which is it's
easier to go up. It's it's harder to
then go back, right? If if suddenly
we're running out of money fast. So what
we could do is we could start with
something a little more bare bones, a
little less generous and then see if we
get more money this coming legislative
session
and then revisit the conversation six
months into next year uh to expand it.
But it's easier to do that and work with
some things that then we have to pull
back. So I'll just stop right there.
Thanks everybody.
Hi. And then to kind of just echo all
of, you know, both what Dominic and
Senator Seinborn says, um, you know,
given that this is just a topic, a
conversation starter, um, and I know
that the last previous, um, conversation
that we had was, you know, to the point
of
should we just focus on
the people who financially need it the
most? Um
and I think that you know as far as the
recommendations kind of going back to
the department of health and this can be
up to discussion for other people as
well is just making sure that it is
clear um kind of to reflect a little bit
both of what Senator Seinborn is saying
but that it's more more of a focus um
and I don't know how to necessarily word
that um but it would be like more of the
focus as as much as the funding can be
utilized to people up to 100%.
And then from there um move towards this
is if there are extra funds beyond that
or something to that effect then we
would move towards like the stages right
this is the sta the first stage is
utilizing the money as much as possible
for the for the most uh uh necessary
then the second stage of utilizing the
funding would be this this this um to
kind of maybe I don't know if that will
mitigate that that language in that kind
of usage. Um because I know that Senator
said something about a burn rate, you
know, and and and you know, are we going
to go through the funding super fast?
But to that point and just to put a pin
in there to me back to the most um and
this might be getting ahead of the of
the game is you know and then back to
the conversation that we're having with
Miguel is people who have the
information first
then you know are usually the people in
the city and who have phones and are on
social media. making sure that the
people who might be mostly affected in
these rural areas or might have harder
ability to get that information that
they have I don't want to say like a
fighting chance but that they are able
to kind of have the accessibility
to know that this this funding because I
can imagine that there are going to be
plenty of people um and I'm not trying
to say that people who have access to
their phones don't need it less but it's
it's just a more of like as soon as a
person is able to process that they
might may or may not need it that they
are able to apply for it or maybe with
people who are hesitant or as you know
like applying for the for the for the uh
the application. I only say that because
it took me a really long time to even
[laughter] apply for insurance because I
was feeling like technologically dumb to
be able to go through the hoops of
getting that together. Um and so I just
I just kind of wanted to make sure that
that was said. There was one more thing
that I had thought about but I think it
was the next slide. Um it was the tiered
format just like stages of that flow. Um
and then also oh so as to what Dominic
and and and um a senator already said
you know yeah if if the funding I guess
is it better that the funding is
utilized and ate up right away with more
people or that we have lingering funds.
I'm not sure which would be the worst of
two evils if if one happens before the
other.
Denali,
your hand is raised.
>> Yeah, I was just curious if the
department I I think it's um
maybe a previous slide the special
category consideration. So like if you
belong to a veteran or if you're a
veteran status or have another um
category,
how how does the department anticipate
this interacting with eligibility? Is it
a both and or um is there
[clears throat] flexibility with income
if
one of those protected?
So, Denali, that's actually why it says
to be determined because this committee
hasn't really discussed that yet as to
how these different criterias other than
just financial could potentially
actually impact the equity fund. And so,
that's really those are some of those
next steps as well.
>> Thank you. Of course, because it's, as
you know, this is one of the aspects
that we keep bringing up that it's not
just about income levels, it's also
about underserved issues.
>> All right. And Chris
Chris, if you're talking, we can't hear
you.
>> Sorry, guys. I
took me a second to find the mute button
today. Um,
no. I I just wanted to say that I agree
with Senator Steinborn that we should
keep this for those who
can't afford it at all and uh
re-evaluate later. I
I agree with the 200% rate, maybe 250,
but um
but I I think that's where we need to
kind of prioritize these funds. And I I
do like like that we are taking into
consideration underserved categories,
but I think
that the bare minimum requirement for
funding should be
uh met uh as a priority over any
anything else.
And
Yeah,
you know, in in my case talking for
veterans,
I think uh a lot of veterans that are
over that line probably have access
through philanthropy or other means. But
there's a lot of veterans
that wouldn't have access to those
things
without
simple some sort of or without P. So I
just think it should be prioritized
that uh is go to the people who can't
afford it
first. Thank you.
Thank you, Chris. Um, Heneifeha,
you'd like to
>> Hi, good afternoon. Can you hear me?
>> Yes.
>> Hello. Hello, everybody. Um, thank you
for this framework and synthesizing this
um sort of baseline for us to to to jam
on here. I think I have just more things
I want to bring up in question for us
all to consider um which is around you
know with the different conditions right
when we think about treatment resistant
depression and PTSD uh for example the
care model for that and the number of
sessions um in terms of preparation the
medicine sessions the kind of included
integration sessions um and then you
know an important like ongoing
integration support. Are we thinking
about a number
a dollar amount that we're saying we the
equity fund would cap for an individual
based like is there a range that I think
we need to consider because someone
might with treatment resistant
depression might just need you know a
smaller care model or or or care team
right and process than someone who has
PTSD who might need multiple dosing
sessions and much more integration
support. Um, so I'm curious if there's
been thought around that um as we're
looking at the uh kind of qualifications
for support.
>> Thank you for that, Hen. Both um you and
Chris for bringing up those two points
as far as um what should be prioritized
first um and or as far as the
considerations.
Just to Chris's point really quickly, I
think I I I do tend to agree with you in
that I think it would be very hard for
me to wrap my head around if
prioritizing like, you know, different
groups of one versus the other uh Native
Americans, veterans rule. I mean, it
could be
just throwing this out there, you know,
if you have like three or four of those
categories and maybe you're like a shoe
in. I don't know. But trying to
prioritize if Native Americans versus a
veteran, I I I
don't know how I would feel about, you
know, juxtaposing one against the other
essentially who gets the treatment. But
I do think for sure how Hanifeha uh you
propose that that it it does kind of
depend on the number of sessions that it
it that we're providing. And in that
kind of extending it just a little bit
more when you're talking about sessions,
it's like back to belonging, back to
this idea of being brought back into the
community. Um are we also kind of
considering all of that as well? you
know, um like not just kind of kicking
someone out to the curb and here's your
suitcase, thank you for the ride, and
then buy. Um it's like the whole system
and how much it will be for like one
particular person. And then it goes back
to this idea $630,000. Are we treating
11 people or are we treating like 300?
And and again, it goes back to like each
number for the sessions. Are we capping
it? Is it is it and I so I think that
like what I'm hearing too is like we
need to add in this idea of like a
survey of the intake of like what it pre
preven like um approval is you know all
of these categories of like what is like
the pre-inte I'm not partic and then
that's requiring you know more um
intersection with
uh patient um systems in our other
committees. I don't know if that makes
sense to anyone, but if anyone would
like to jump in, that would be great.
We've got like 30 more minutes.
>> Can I just bump on that? What you just
Am I still mute unmuted?
>> Yes.
>> Okay. I I think what you're also
I'm really lifting up within this and
what we have the opportunity to make
some decisions around um you know it it
is about
um this this idea that we presented on
before which I think we leaned on like
the the signing up for this would be
more on the providers and not
necessarily on the individuals because
individuals they not they might not know
like okay I know okay I have PTS
So I'm going to need these many
treatments and these many sessions of
integration. They might they're not
going to I'm assuming right not be aware
of like what that even means. And so
there will need to be some synergy and
communication and understanding between
providers and the patients right um in
terms of okay we're thinking at max
you're going to need like these many
sessions that that includes prep the
medicine sessions and integration. Um so
that that is a very interesting and
important part of all of this.
Yeah. Yeah. And sorry Chris, I'm just
going to jump in like really quickly,
you know, because I've heard from a
number of people that they're still on
the idea and I know we've gone past this
in the conversations, but you know, this
is going to go out to the greater
public, you know, wanting to do micro
doing, wanting to just try it out,
wanting, you know, and and and so we
really need to think about being
forthcoming about the criteria that
we're looking for of that, you know, if
it's evaluated that you're at, you know,
three or four sessions and this is
including what is included, right? this
whole buffet of of care, right? Then
this is, you know, then this will be
like for you because there's going to be
a lot of people are going to be and I
know we can't make everyone happy.
There's going to be a lot of
disappointment, but being upfront with,
you know, what it's what are the
categories and why um that it's going to
be that you absolutely are not able to
take, you know, pay for the medicine at
all. Um that it's from mild to moderate.
from a scale of like 1 to 10, you're
between like, you know, a four and a six
on that scale, whatever the scales or
whatever the criteria might be. And so
that they know that if they hit the
three, they're not going to be a part of
the session. If they hit the seven,
they're not going to be a part of the
session. That we're really looking for a
very the liinal spaces in between of
what who we're looking at. Um I I think
is really good points, Anife Chris.
>> No, I I just wanted to be clear. I
wasn't
I wasn't suggesting that veterans be
placed over Native Americans or any
other population. I was I was trying to
say that the
economic
uh requirements should come first and
that that way we are treating those who
do could not access this medicine any
other way.
>> Totally. And I was trying to e echo what
you were saying that that should be the
first priority because I didn't want to
get into those places of trying to say
that, you know, as a Native American, I
feel like, you know, we should be
treated because we're the First Nations
people. I don't want to start getting
into those kinds of arguments. And um so
I feel like having it just be about the
financial is really important, but how
do we integrate these other criterias?
And I want to say that maybe the rural
one, I don't know. I don't know. So this
is the question to you all I think to
all to us is you know how much value do
we place on this idea of other
categories and there was even an other
other categories
um you know if you're a single parent
I'm not sure if that would even be like
one of the criterias but because there's
going to be a multitude of different
people in different demographics and and
cultural practices and and and
ethnicities ities and everything
that have and I I can't even I'm I can't
even say right that are their the their
situation is like I need to do this and
I'll I'll go ahead and say it as a
single mother caretaking say like for my
elderly folks and you know being trapped
in the middle maybe it would be me in
the quote the other categories maybe I'm
not Native American um but who you know
for those types of people in those
particular types of categories
and or or mothers who are have a yeah
let's advocate for the mothers who are
having um postpartum depressions or
anything like that you know like what
are those other categories where it's
just like these the individuals are at
their wits end and they really need um
help and it's been very very difficult.
So what are those other considerations?
Um, my suggestion for any kind of
thought and I'll go back and defer to
the rest of the Department of Health or
anyone else is do we go ahead and have a
strict criteria that we're only going to
look at financial means um prior
prioritizing that as Chris suggests
um and cap it at 200 250.
The only thing that I would further
suggest is that it's a stage in stages
of like we're going to up until the the
funds are then completely distributed.
This is how we're going to distribute
the funds and until the funds are
completely uh distributed then this is
how we're going to go with a scale of up
to 200%.
Second stage is if we still have funds
that may or may not be available. I
don't know if this may or may not work
because I'm not a monies person. Then
we're going to go to going to the 300%.
The only reason why I appreciate these
the um tiered chart is just so that like
what if we have leftover? What are we
going to do with that if everybody
within a period of time um are we just
going to hold on to the funds till we
get a new application? Is there an
application period? Like when I say
period, I mean, you know, application
deadline is this. Or is it just going to
keep, you know, we have $30,000 left in
the bank and we're still waiting for
someone to apply? I those are just the
scenarios that are coming to my head and
I've never been in a place to look at
this. So, I don't know if that's even
worth mentioning. Um, so anyone else who
wants to chime in
the meantime, I'll go ahead and read
these chats.
Um, I think we kind of sort of answered
the one about, let's see, Greg asked
about the f federal poverty line level
based on MAGI
modified adjusted gross income, which is
adjusted income plus non-T taxable
income. Uh, okay. Is there data about
how many New Mexicans are in each income
bracket? That would be interesting.
division of the fund might be more
equitable based on the income of people
in particular levels. Maybe there could
be a starting aortionment based on
qualified condition type. So there is
not a run on the fund in one category.
Okay, I like that idea. So let me see if
I could get this straight as far as what
Senator Steinborn is saying. Retreatment
treatment uh resistant depression versus
let's just say anxiety. I know they kind
of go hand in hand, but um let's just
for the sake of argument split them. Um
we're going to allow for 10 people with
treatment uh resistant depression and 10
people with anxiety. When we've gotten
through those 10 slots for the people
with depression, then we move on to a
different category of with people with
anxiety and so forth and so forth. that
may or may not seem interesting to look
at.
Um, and I think
Dominic answered a question that Don
Moser had. And if we don't have uh
Senator Steinborn, would you go ahead
and unmute your mic?
>> Okay. Yeah. So, thanks. Thanks, Joseph.
Yeah. So to clarify, you know, my one
scenario I I could see happening is
there could be a practitioner or group
of practitioners are particularly
skilled at utilizing the fund. in which
case you could see a bunch of
applications come in in one category
even related to a couple practices and
and that you know and our rules would
unless we create some barriers
would allow that right and so what I'm
saying is if you say okay there's a
threshold there even though we will
prove to be imperfect no
certain um nonetheless we would kind of
protect the fund at least to start with
so that people with a different
condition which might you know let's
look at PTSD and first responders that
might disproportionately be dealing with
that than than end of life anxiety
obviously which is going to be a
different population and so by having
kind of a portionment more like saying
25% of the fund right or whatever that
is $150,000 could go towards this as
opposed to a number of patients um could
go towards this then we assured that if
suddenly there is a heavy demand in one
category another that we're not cutting
off some of the other people that no
doubt need it that you know that their
practitioners aren't as skilled at going
after this money. So that's what I'm
saying. It's just kind of a protection
to start with to protect ourselves from
that scenario and sure that you know
we're helping as many people in the
different categories as possible and
again also on the income level that'll
also make sure we spread it out and you
know I think invariably when we get into
this we're going to see are we over are
we utilizing it much faster than we
thought are we utilizing it slower can
we expand out are these categories
unnecessary I think they're all good
safeguards to start with to be a little
more conservative and then you know
clearly we're going to need to try to
get more money and depending upon our
success in that we can and more
information we could adjust this you
know middle part of next year.
So anyway, thanks Bob.
>> Yeah, and I honestly, you know, just
because you brought it up, um I think
that that also dovtales nicely into the
research aspect of it, you know, because
then all of this is going to go back
into how do we improve, you know, what
our SWAT is going to be at the end of
all of this and during is what are the
strengths, the weaknesses, you know, the
outcomes of everything that we're doing.
Um, and it'll just kind of start feeding
into itself. You know, where do we where
is this fund? And then the specifically
with demographics in the rural areas or
populations as they're filling out and
as they're providing the information as
they hopefully we can we can have that
then we'll know further on and have that
data available when we're you know
asking for more money.
Uh, Denali,
>> thanks. Um [snorts] yeah, grateful for
the generative conversation here and in
addition to the senator's recommendation
around um [clears throat]
assuring like building in asurances that
that um all of our qualifying conditions
are represented. One of the
recommendations we made the last time
that we met is um you know not just
indications but that there is geographic
representation. Um, I think something
that uh will fall into um any one of our
categories is making sure um too that we
uh have access for providers who
specialize in homebound use, right? Um
so that that population
uh receives access to the fund too. And
and I just want to say that the
department in other areas um is really
used to making these categories and and
that they're helpful for ensuring equity
and ensuring in other instances, you
know, public health. They think about
vaccine clinics and the way that those
[clears throat] the way that the funds
to to administer those are are are based
in certain metrics um for success uh
[clears throat] around you know both
patient demographics and um and
geography. So um I feel really trusting
of the department's ability. And to the
senator's final point about you know um
our future asks the more the more
information the more we require of um
the fund and how it's administered based
on you know who uh making decisions and
determinations about who um and where
the money goes. All of that will be data
that will be available to the
legislature, you know, that we can say
um because we'll be collecting it at the
outset, you know, the fund treated this
many people with um whatever indication
in whatever geographic part of the of
the state or um you know, any of the
other qualifications that we that we
come up with as a group is going to be
more information for the legis
legislature about how the funds were
used. Um, and yeah, that we're in this
reputation building moment of the first
time that there's been this allocation.
And it's really, yeah, the job of the
community and the department and
everyone um to to demonstrate that we
use the money. Well,
>> thank you for that, Denali.
Uh, thank you, Senator Steinborn. Um,
[laughter]
I feel like we should vote on something,
but maybe we shouldn't. We've only got
20 minutes left. Um is there anybody who
has like a completely you know who who
really feels for or against the idea of
moving in the direction of you know just
what we talked about so far. Just to
kind of recap, we've got a lot of people
who say that we should just mostly focus
on the financial um ability of a person
to pay and then you know capping it at a
specific number. But we also have this
idea of
um
you know taking into account uh
different presenting symptoms.
Um also geographic location which to me
is you know the rule. Um we don't I
don't want you know majority of the pe
well it you know the medicine will go
wherever it it's it's needed. I'll just
say that I I trust
that everything will work as it's as as
it's needed in how it will fall. I trust
the ability of making the right
decisions for all of us that it'll that
we will be able to come to a consensus
on how this is going to be distributed
to the best of our ability. Not going to
say I'm just going to leave it to
chance. Um but
we'll we'll be able to take into the
considerations what what is necessary to
create the framework to create the
environment um that is necessary. Um,
Hanifeha,
>> hi. Yes, I just wanted to reiterate if
we're, you know, this presentation was
on the financial requirements um and
determinations and again um there I feel
like there's something more. Obviously,
there's a lot more, but we're taking
this a step at a time. But in terms of
understanding how far can that 6:30
stretch, if we're talking about
uh a care model that is like five
sessions or a care model that might be
like up to 12 sessions, you know, with
everything included. So, I just am
wondering how how we're going to factor
that in to this.
Do we have any mathematicians
in our midst? We need I need to find a
mathematician because I feel like this
is we got the as we're approaching zero
we need to find within this space under
this curve how we're going to be able to
you know with this variable adding this
in with you know all of this stuff.
There has to be a formula where if we
just kind of toggle all of this
information, it'll spit out the answer.
Dominic,
>> thank you, Desba. And thank you,
Heneife, for for the question. Uh, and
we've answered parts of this before, but
we don't know yet. And the main reason
is because as we work and we determine
how much, for example, would be
reimbursed to a provider for through um
Medicaid or through insurance, you know,
we're going to need to see about putting
a cap on what that that amount is. So,
for example, a therapist who normally
would charge $100 for example or $120
for an hourlong session and suddenly
because the patient is eligible for the
um uh for the equity fund, they decide
to suddenly charge $300. That's not
going to be allowed. So, one of the
things that we've been doing with HCA
and with Medicaid is looking at what
those reimburseable amounts are and that
will cap some of that. [clears throat]
Um, so looking at that not just for
Medicaid but also with regard to
insurance, how much do they reimburse as
a maximum? So that's going to actually
affect some of this as well. Um and then
the other aspect and and it was noted on
one of actually two of the slides that
this also depends on how much is going
to be reimburseed through those programs
because the equity fund will not the
equity fund comes after all of those
other reimbursements can potentially
happen. So if you have someone who's on
Medicaid, they go through the program
and Medicaid is paying for most of the
treatment. So the therapy sessions, all
of that aspect, then the equity fund
would really just be used for the cost
of the medicine and potentially that
administration session. So that also
changes what that factor is. But until
we know a little bit more about
who is actually even applying for the
program, what patients are being seen,
what other programs, insurance,
Medicaid, etc. are they actually
eligible for? We're not going to have a
really good feel on that. We can make a
few assumptions on it, but again, part
of that is going to depend on how much
is being paid through those other
mechanisms. And so remember, the equity
fund is there for those who cannot
afford it. It's also there, you could
think of it in some ways as sort of the
last resort. So the payer of last
resort. And so we have to figure some of
those other parts out. We're working on
that with HCA for what are some
potential um you know uh what are some
potential um mechanisms for it and what
are some of the potential uh
possibilities as far as who as far as
patients what categories that fall in
who can get reimbured who can't and once
we have some more of that over the next
couple of months we should be able to
actually come up with some firmer
projections but at this point we don't
have that just yet because that's
extraordinarily complex and it will also
determine somewhat on what the other
categories are for when what people uh
as far as what their conditions are and
what conditions will make them eligible
for the equity. I think some of this
discussion with regard to it and putting
some numbers there as far as what does
the different percentages of poverty
level has already been very helpful
because I know we had some concerns
about that when some of these original
suggestions were coming up and so I'm
really glad that we're having that
conversation and people are starting to
see and think a little more about
numbers but for those we don't quite
have those projections yet.
I hope that helps.
Yeah, thank you. Thank you, Dominic. And
I I think you know given all of that
then in this conversation the 400% that
you all kind of presented at and then
this initial in the previous meeting was
like 250.
I I don't know. It feels like we kind of
maybe want to move toward picking a
number. [laughter] Um, and personally I
think like something closer to 300 feels
equitable to me given that there's so
much unknown about if people are
Medicaid or not, what will be covered,
what won't be. Um, because like $64,000
is is
right to me is feels very low, right?
And then you're talking about, you know,
folding in this type of care. So I I I
wouldn't want to make assumptions that
64 is you know um too is is too
expensive like is someone making too
much money you know to to to fill in
this type of care given we don't know we
don't know the other variables of what
will be covered. So I in my humble
opinion and my suggestion will be 300
300%.
And I'm going to step off of my little
soap box now. Goodbye.
>> Thank you, Anita. [laughter]
And I think that was kind of my original
thought. Um, you know, when I had
proposed the 300 initially was
and it's hard to kind of juggle and keep
all of these things in my mind that, you
know, that it's it's after it's after we
have all the coupons and so forth, you
know, this is what we're dealing with,
right? Um, and to put it in those kind
of terms for me to to see and think
about. Um but it is a matter of like I
think we just need to kind of come up
[laughter]
we we me all of us need to come up with
you know various different uh formulas
math formulas where if a person you know
after we've had you know uh Medicaid
this this this and this covering at an
average of whatever then this is what
this could potentially look like which
is why I keep going back to are we
treating 10 people 11 people are you're
treating 300 people because it just
depends on how much money you know we're
actually it's going to take for a full
uh I'm going to say like a full session
a full therapy session which includes
however many sub subessions right um and
so forth so I think it's really good to
kind of think about you know it it's
it's we need to start kind of coming up
with the N's and the Y's and the B's and
everything is like how are these
variables going to contribute um and
think about
to hold on to this idea. Um,
and and I I will I will also agree to
some degree to some degree
in Santa Fe. There's there's like I
don't know. I don't know how anyone
could possibly, you know, there's
there's just no way, you know, like you
have to be making was it
130 something just to ek out an
existence and there's plenty of us that
are not anywhere near that. Nowhere near
that. So, how is it to say that like 600
is too much?
That it's too much when I'm talking
about 600% above the poverty line. I
totally understand it. I totally get
that. Um but that back to Senator
Seinborn's um uh point, you know, we're
also looking at statewide.
We're not just looking at Santa Fe. And
so
this is where the headache comes in
where someone is considered poor in
Santa Fe, they're not going to be
considered quote poor, you know, in
living in Espanola. You know, it's
you're it's easier for someone to be
able to to be
So, this is where I'm saying like it
gets to be a little confusing when we're
talking about 300% but I I think we also
need to think about, you know, statewide
and keep that in mind. Greg, we have 10
minutes left and I
>> just on that statewide consideration,
the math exists. The adjusted gross, the
modified adjusted gross handles that a
lot. like you know say for example
somebody makes $64,000 a year they spend
35 of that on rent that's a part of
their adjusted gross income and you have
to consider all of that so in Santa Fe
when your rent is an exorbitant
exorbitant percentage of your total
overall income and the other costs of
living are calculated into that like
just understand that that that like it's
it there are other entities that have
handled this and we can leverage those
um models. Um as Denali pointed to
earlier, qu one question I have if
Dominic has time to address this. I
cannot remember for the life of me. Is
there is there a conversation
in place around regulating in any manner
the cost of
goods as opposed to the cost of
services?
if that's clear. So
>> yeah, Greg, uh you're just saying are we
essentially going to put prices on how
much the products cost and the answer
>> more so is there a conversation around
that? I can't remember if that happened
>> and it did happen uh when we were doing
some of the production side and we're
not able to uh to do that. That would
actually um that's something that the
market itself has to determine what
those are. However, again, as I was
mentioning with regard to
uh reimbursement for like therapy hours,
the time of the therapist and all of
that, we can do something very similar
to that with regard to the equity fund
that if someone is eligible on the
equity fund, the cost of the medication
cannot be more than X amount. Um, but
that would have to be determined. I hope
that helps. So, I mean, yeah, like it it
it's interesting because there's this
threshold where the the free market can
allow for a lower price if there is a
greater market and if the if things that
happen in Colorado and Oregon occur
where they're only, you know, tiny
little funnels to get product to market
and then the the product end up ends up
calling costing like $500 a dose, then
it becomes insane.
So I Yeah. Yeah. And but I think if
there's a I I don't know if [sighs] if I
want to say this out loud, but if
there's a way to like hide the cost
through services, [laughter]
um that might be I don't know. Um
yeah, I just look forward to it not
being a problem for people to access.
Anyways, thanks. That's all.
>> Thank you. And and I would um just say
oh I see Denali put her hand up but
before we go to Denali we do need to set
the next meeting. Um and uh I mean maybe
Denali if you want to be really fast
>> we can
>> uh I was just going to say
>> at the 14th
[gasps]
>> I'll put it in the chat.
>> Okay. Thank you Danelli. We just do need
to make sure that uh you know that um
that we finish on time today um because
we do have some other commitments as
well. So didn't despair.
Was that correct, Despa? You were
talking Oh, I see that. So, I think you
were saying on the 14th um uh the uh the
14th of July the department actually has
a conflict. We have a different public
meeting with regard to cannabis uh
starting at 3. So, we wouldn't be able
to do that. We would be able to do one
o'clock if that would work. Um or we
could look at the following week, which
is the 21st.
>> Yeah.
>> Would the 21st be fine?
Uh
>> yes, I see your thumbs up, Desba. Okay,
so we will put it at uh the 21st uh
again starting at 3:00.
Okay.
Well, thank you everybody. We appreciate
it. Um Desba, I do see that your audio
is messed up. Um so I'll go ahead, if
it's okay, I will go ahead and close
out. um uh the meeting. Thank you
everybody for being here. Thank you
Denali. I just saw what you put in the
chat as far as one of the items is uh
controlling the cost through the testing
requirements. Burdensome testing
requirements are primarily was driven
the cost in Oregon and Colorado. Uh
definitely agreed. Um we have checked
with several of the testing labs and it
does not look like the testing
requirements are going to be burdensome.
Um and uh but um uh that's a whole we
could talk about that forever. Um and
then um uh with that in mind, oh thank
you Greg. Um yeah, those are uh the
rules actually can be found um on the um
record and archive New Mexico record and
archive website. Um and then we will be
posting it to our site as well. Um it
just takes a few days for those for
those requests to go through our IT
department. Um so you can look for
those. Um and uh we'll try to put it
here in the chat um here in just a
moment. Um and then other than that,
we'd like to thank everybody for
participating today. It was great
discussion. Really appreciate it. And um
definitely uh more um things to come up.
Oh, and Jorge does have it in the chat,
although it's just labeled as new. Um,
but [laughter]
and it is new,
but uh so they are available. So, with
that, thank you everybody. We hope you
all have a great day and uh we'll see
you all in a few weeks.